Wilson, Ernest Henry, 1876-1930. Papers of Ernest Henry Wilson, 1896-1952: Guide.
Papers of Ernest Henry Wilson, 1896-1952.
- W.IX: Expedition Photographs in Bound Volumes and Related Materials
  - Box 15
    - Folder 1: Photographs of Ernest Henry Wilson taken during Expeditions, Individual and Group
      - EHW in Tasmania, 1920. (4 different photographs)
      - EHW posed with two unidentified men, no date. (1 photograph)
      - EHW in Singapore. (1 photograph)
      - Mr. and Mrs. Ernest Henry Wilson and Muriel with 3 unidentified women in Asia? (1 photograph)
    - Folder 2
      - Photographs of herbarium material and labels, summer 1980.
    - Folder 3
      - Water Lilies and Japanese Iris believed to have been taken in City Park, Springfield, MA, July 10, 1927. (9 different photographs, 2 copies of m447), NOTE: on Photograph labeled m453—Writing on back of photograph describes this image as "Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, London, England. Water lily pond. Japanese iris in foreground. Your Mother used to play here as a small child." Kew disputes location.
    - Folder 4
      - IMS Grant for Wilson Archives 1985, and typed notes. Plant Science Arnold Arboretum Newsletter v.5(1) Fall/Winter 1985 and v.6(1) Fall/Winter 1985-86.
    - Folder 5
      - BGBase printout listing all of Wilson's glass plate negatives with modernized nomenclature.
    - Folder 6
      - “In search of Ernest Henry Wilson – Dec 2002;” DVD-RW, 5 photographs with notes by Dean Ho on recreating Wilson’s images, “The Asia Center at Harvard University” brochure that inspired Ho’s project.
    - Compact Disc
      - "Wilson Glass Negative Wilson Print Testing 06/01" (Harvard College Library Digital Imaging Group)
    - Mini Compact Disc 1
      - "Wilson's Sungpan Yesterday ... Today," July 12, 2004. Created by Dean Ho who retraced Wilson's trip to Song Pan in 1910 and re-photographed several of Wilson's landscapes in 2004.
    - Mini Compact Disc 2
      - "Wilson's Sungpan Yesterday ... Today," July 12, 2004. 2nd copy.
  - Box 16 (oversized), Please see Wilson's Photograph Books for accurate documentation. One copy unless otherwise noted.
    - Series Z: Expedition to China 1907-1909.
      - Z-25. Pistacia chinensis. Tree 80 ft. x 12 ft. (male). Near City of Wan Hsien. Yangtsze river, April 1908. (2 copies)
      - Z- 26. Juniperus chinensis. Tree 25-30 ft. high. Often planted among graves. Wan Hsien, Yangtsze River, April 1, 1908.
      - Z-29. Ficus lacor. Tree 50 ft. x 15 ft. Head 90 ft. through. Wan Hsien, Yangtsze River, April 1, 1908 (BGBase Acc 1973). (2 copies—both missing from box.)
      - Z-39. Ficus lacor. Tree 40 ft. x 12 ft. Head 60 ft. through. With shrine and opium poppy, April 16, 1908. (5 copies, a)from 35mm negative b)digitized from glass plate—all missing from box.)
      - Z-58. Pterocarya stenoptera. Typical farm-house on Chentu Plain with Cypress and Bamboos, May 14, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2002). (2 copies)
      - Z-91. Vidam groups of Bom-Po (Phallic) religion. Tunglin shan Temple, May 31, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2035).
      - Z-101. Machilus bournei. Temple with Bamboo and Nanmu trees. 2700 ft., June 16, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2045).
      - Z-102. The An-Lan chio. Bamboo suspension bridge 300 yards long, June 16, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2046).
      - Z-106. Hsuan Kou. Typical riverine village of western Szechuan, June 17, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2050). (2 copies)
      - Z-110. Lilium giganteum. White flowers. Niu-tou-shan, June 20, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2054). (2 copies)
      - Z-128. Primula veitchii. At home. Flowers rosy pink. Alt. 11,500 ft., June 23, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2072).
      - Z-129. Cypripedium tibeticum. At home. Flowers dark red. Alt. 11,500 ft., June 23, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2073).
      - Z-130. Cypripedium tibeticum. At home. Flowers dark red. Uplands Pan-lan-shan, June 23, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2074). (2 copies)
      - Z-132. Primula. Combined Hostel and Temple, June 23, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2076). (2 copies)
      - Z-137. Meconopsis integrifolia. Miscellaneous alpine flowers. Uplands Pan- lan-shan. Alt. 13,000 ft., June 24, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2081).
      - Z-169. Picea retroflexa. Tree 60 to 70 ft. x 5 to 8 ft. Forests of Ta-pao-shan. Alt. 10,500 ft., July 5, 1908.
      - Z-193. Larix potaninii. "Batalin" Tree 60 ft. x 8 ft. Forests of the Ta-pao-shan, July 7, 1908.
      - Z-194. Rheum alexandrae. Flowers pale yellow spikes 3 ft. 6 in. high and Primula involucrata. 13,000 ft., July 7, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2138).
      - Z-197. View of snow-clad peaks 21,000 ft. or more, July 7, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2141).
      - Z-199. View of snow-clad peaks 21,000 ft. or more, July 7, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2143).
      - Z-204. Caravan and gear which crossed from Kuan Hsien to Tachien-lu, July 9, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2148).
      - Z-218. The Ya-chia-k'an snows and alpine region, July 19, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2162)., NOTE: Z-218 and Z-219 mounted on same board, both images reversed.
      - Z-219. Tachien-lu and site of ancient town demolished by landslide, July 27, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2163).
      - Z- 244. Slate slabs with figures of Buddha and the mystic prayer, "Om ...," July 29, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2188). (3 copies)
      - Z-246. Lilium thayerae growing in a garden. Alt. 8,400 ft., July 30, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2190). (2 copies)
      - Z-248. View in ravine of the Tachien-lu river. This stream falls 4,000 ft. in less than 20 miles. Alt. 6,000 ft., July 30, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2192). (2 copies)
      - Z-249. Men laden with "Brick Tea." One man's load weighs 317 lbs., July 30, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2193). (3 copies, 1 negative)
      - Z-270. Diospyros lotus. Tree 80 ft. x 12 ft. Foot of Fei-Yueh-Ling, August 3, 1908. (2 copies)
      - Z-279. Ching chi Hsien from distance. Ta-Hsien-ling Mountains in mists, August 5, 1908. (3 copies)
      - Z-285. Nelumbium speciosum. Flowers pink in pond. Alt. 2,000 ft., August 10, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2229).
      - Z-286. "Pai-lu" memorial arch to memory of a virtuous widow, a common wayside feature of the west, August 10, 1908. (3 copies)
      - Z-291. Pavilion with ornate stone pillars. Alt. 1,700 ft. Ching Yang Temple, August 18, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2235). (3 copies)
      - Z-297. Broussonetia papyrifera in the foreground. Alt. 1,700 ft., August 22, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2241).
      - Z-299. Machilus bournei. Pavilion side of river with Bamboo and Nanmu trees. Alt. 1,700 ft., August 24, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2243).
      - Z-324. Hamlet of Ping-ling-shih with Mt. Wa-wu in the distance. Alt. 31,350 ft., September 8, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2268).
      - Z-329. Summit of Mt. Wa-wu. Abies Delavayi, September 10, 1908.
      - Z-385. Ormosia hosiei. Sedan chair, November 11, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2329).
      - Z-402. Foot of Ting Shin Shan, W. Szechuan. View of ravine, showing house and general vegetation. Alt. 5,000 ft., October 28, 1908.
      - Z-405. British Consulate, Chentu. Center: EHW, November 4, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2349). (2 copies)
      - Z-408. Collection of rare and valuable vases, November 4, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2352).
      - Z-419. Collection of valuable porcelain, property of Prof. Smith, November 19,1908 (BGBase Acc 2363). (3 copies)
      - Z-420. Collection of valuable porcelain, property of Mr. Kung. November 9, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2364). (2 copies)
      - Z-432. Raft used for navigating the shallow and rapid Ya River, built of Bambusa vulgaris stems, also bag of 53 duck and miscellaneous birds, December 9, 1908.
      - Z-436. "The Harvard boat with boy and boat captain on roof." Kiating Fu, December 13, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2380).
      - Z-450. Mantzu cave with ornate facade, fashioned by a race now extinct, December 22, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2394). (3 copies)
      - Z-472. Xylosma congestum. Pubescens tree 55 x 6 ft. With snow planted among graves, January 20, 1909 (BGBase Acc 2394).
      - Z-484. General view of country to the south of Ichang, January 21, 1909. (2 copies)
      - Z-589. Packing lily-bulbs. Ichang, February 2, 1909. (2 copies, image reversed on 1)
      - Z-600. EHW and boy with pheasants, 1909.
      - Z-635. Ulmus parvifolia. Tree 25 ft. x 6 ft., Dalbergia hupeana, Hance on tomb, February 27, 1909.
      - Z-639. Tomb with stone effigies of horses, tigers, cats, deer, men, etc. with a temple, February 28, 1909. (2 copies)
      - Z-644. Ichang Fu, W. Hupeh, March 1, 1909.
      - Z-697. Davidia sp., no date.
      - Z-711. Native craft lined up in tiers. March 3, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2755).
      - Z-713. Primula sinensis. Flowers mauve pink, at home, limestone cliffs. Alt. 120 ft., March 5, 1908 (BGBase Acc 2757).
      - No number. "The Harvard" with crew, December 13, 1908. (3 copies).
  - Box 17 (oversized)
    - Folder 1: Series N: Expedition to Eastern Asia, 1917-1919
      - N-15. Liukiu houses, East Asia, February 26, 1917.
      - N-89. Haha-jima (west coast) from Nagaphama, Muko-jima on horizon, April 27, 1917 (BGBase Acc 89).
      - N-111. Oo-ryong-too (Dagelet Island) northeast coast, general view, June 1, 1917 (BGBase Acc 111).
      - N-134. Dodo, chief port of Oo-ryong-too (Dagelet Island), June 15, 1917 (BGBase Acc 134).
      - N-311. Quercus glauca. Vegetation on Quelpaert Island, with Quercus glandulifera, November 2, 1917 (BGBase Acc 311).
      - N-585. Pinus densiflora. On cliffs, broad-leafed trees in foreground, September 11, 1918 (BGBase Acc 585).
    - Folder 2. Series X: Expedition to Japan, 1914
      - X-140. Prunus subhirtella var. pendula Tanaka. Tree 30 ft. x 10 ft.; crown 50ft. through. Kogetsu Temple, Ongata village, near Tokyo. Arnold Arboretum Expedition to Japan, 1914, volume 5, p. 442, April 1, 1914.
      - X-317. Pinus thunbergii. With four Pinus densiflora. S. and Z. in foreground, sandstone, June 30, 1914 (BGBase Acc 1268). (2 copies)
      - X-335. Pinus thunbergii. Furo-zan, remarkable cliffs of gray limestone, July 8, 1914 (BGBase Acc 1286). (2 copies)
      - X-394. Unidentified. (2 copies)
      - X-564. Sciadopitys verticillata var. Pendula 80 ft. x 9 ft. With down-curved branches; habit very unusual (BGBase Acc 1515). (2 copies)
      - X-603. Ginkgo biloba. 50 ft. x 30 ft. (BGBase Acc 1554). (2 copies)
    - Series O: Expedition to China, 1910-1911
      - O-2. View across the Yangtze River opposite Ichang with net and small boats used in fishing with otters, February 22, 1911 (BGBase Acc 1572).
      - O-11. View of terraced hills and cliffs, no identifying information.
      - O-18. Cornus kousa. A branch, flowers 5 inches across. Alt. 3,500 ft., June 6, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1588). (2 copies)
      - O-19. Rosa multiflora var. cathayensis. A fine form with pink flowers, side of stream, June 6, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1589). (2 copies)
      - O-20. A yellow man's burden! Weight about 267 lbs., June 6, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1590). (3 copies)
      - O-29. Gleditsia macracantha. Farmhouse with Bamboo and "soap" tree, February 23, 1911.(2 copies)
      - O-54. Our lodgings. Peasant's home at Hsien-tien-tsu, June 11,1910 (BGBase Acc 1624). (2 copies)
      - O-72. General view of country in northwest Hupeh. Peaks 5,000 ft., June 14, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1642).
      - O-84. Hostel Fang-hsien, Hupeh, June 15, 1910.
      - O-100. Hostel hotel of Hsao-lung t'ang. Alt. 7,000 ft. With bee hives, June 16, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1670).
      - O-114. Liriodendron chinense. Tree 60 ft. x 7 ft., June 21, 1910. (2 copies)
      - O-135. Rheum officinale. Cultivated for medicine. Alt. 6,000 ft., June 24, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1705. (2 copies)
      - O-140. View near Hupeh—Szechuan boundary from Szechuan side, June 24, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1710).
      - O-143. General view, limestone cliffs 3,000 ft. above camera, June 24, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1713).
      - O-151. Wayside shrine with votive offerings to tutelary genius, June 25, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1721).
      - O-159. Some inhabitants of Taning Hsien, victims of their own curiosity, June 27, 1910. (3 copies)
      - O-167. Salix babylonica and bridge. Pine woods beyond. Alt. 1,000 ft. June 29, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1737). (2 copies)
      - O-172. Thea sinensis. An ordinary plantation, bushes 3-5 ft. high, Grove of Bamboo. June 29, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1742). (2 copies)
      - O-185. Eucommia ulmoides. Man carrying load of Tu-chang bark, a valued tonic medicine, July 1, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1755).
      - O-188. Exit from natural tunnel 50 yards long. Alt. 2,500 ft., July 1, 1911 (BGBase Acc 1758).
      - O-193. "A study in architecture," castle of rich family named T'ao, July 2, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1763).
      - O-201. North Central Szechuan, cliff in red sandstone region. Tung-Haiang Hsien, Alt. 2,500 ft., July 6, 1910. (missing from box)
      - O-203. Lilium formosum. At home on sandstone cliff. Alt. 2,500 ft., July 9, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1773).
      - O-214. Pistacia chinensis. Sandstone bridge with Cypress and Bamboo. Alt 2,100 ft. July 14, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1784).
      - O-215. Lilium formosum. Flowers, white, interior suffused with yellow. Alt 2,100 ft., July 14, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1785). (2 copies)
      - O-217. Teng-Kou covering an O-me-to-fu stone, covered by hats to keep off sun and rain, July 15, 1910.
      - O-221 Albizzia kalkora. Tree 70 ft. x 10 ft. With corn-stack in foreground to right, July 17, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1791). (2 copies)
      - O-232. Sapindus mukorossii. Tree 80 ft. x 12 ft. With small pagoda and inn. Alt. 2,100 ft., July 21, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1802). (2 copies)
      - O-234. Platycodon grandiflorum. Field cultivated for medicinal purposes. Alt. 1,900 ft., July 25, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1804). (2 copies)
      - O-242. Machine used for spinning cotton, with peasant woman in holiday dress, February 6, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1812). (2 copies)
      - O-255. View from Peh-yang-chang looking in direction of Sungpan. August 16, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1825).
      - O-256. Buddleia davidii. Bush 6 ft., flowers rich violet purple. Alt. 5,000 ft. August 16, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1826).
      - O-259. Bamboo suspension bridge 65 yards long. Alt. 2,700 ft. August 12, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1829). (2 copies)
      - O-260. Showing structure of Bamboo suspension bridge, August 12, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1830)., NOTE: Removed for digitization Nov. 9, 2001.
      - O-273. Lilium brownii. Flowers white, red-purple without. Alt. 7,000 ft., August 16, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1843).
      - O-284. Gentiana. A beautiful plant with carmine red flowers. Alt. 9,000 ft. August 21, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1854).
      - O-296. The hostel of San-chia-tsze. Alt. 12,500 ft., August 23, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1866).
      - O-311. View of Sungpan valley looking north from east gate, September 25, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1881).
      - O-319. Two peasants, tribesmen, on to right. Sifau, August 25, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1889).
      - O-341. "Indispensables." Men laden with sandals made from Bamboo, August 31, 1910 (BGBase Acc 1911).
      - O-342. Tea for Sung-Pan market, Min Valley, August 31, 1910.
      - O-356. "My Chinese collectors, all faithful and true, Ichang," February 15, 1911 (BGBase Acc 1926).
      - O-362. E. Hupeh, "The ford of Kiu-Ling (Yo-Chow) entrance to Tung-Ting Lake with lake craft," February 26, 1911.
      - O-363. The Treaty port of Shasi on Yangtze River, 900 miles from mouth, February 25, 1911.
      - O-367. Boats and nets used in fishing with otters, February 23, 1911 (BGBase Acc 1937).
      - O-368. Otter used locally in fishing, February 23, 1911 (BGBase Acc 1938). (2 copies)
- W.X: Maps and Travel Handbooks
  - Box 18
    - Folder 1
      - China. Map of Western Hupeh and Szechuan. Photographic reproduction of map with caption: "A naturalist in Western China." EHW's travel route marked, no date.
    - Folder 2
      - Area map of Szechuan. Photographic reproduction, no date.
    - Folder 3
      - Enlarged area map of Szechuan. Photographic reproduction, no date.
    - Folder 4
      - Korea. "Map of Chosen Railways." Two identical maps. One of the maps has notations in EHW's handwriting.
    - Folder 5
      - Japan. "Imperial government railways." Railroad map with areas circled. No date.
    - Folder 6
      - Hand-drawn map of "Kawanabe-Islands" with notation: "The red limit, collected or footed." No date.
    - Folder 7
      - "Arisan railway, Formosa," published by Arisan Forestry Bureau, 1913.
    - Folder 8
      - "Formosa (or Taiwan)." Travel handbook with map, published by Japan Tourist Bureau, Formosa, 1916.
    - Folder 9
      - "General map showing the geological formation and mineral distribution of Formosa, Japan." Published by Bureau of Productive Industries, Formosan Government, 1909. Notations on minerals by Wilson.
    - Folder 10
      - New Zealand. "Map of the South Island." Reverse side shows: "Map of the North Island," no date.
    - Folder 11
      - Australia. "Map of Western Australia," 1920.
    - Folder 12
      - India. "India showing railways." Map prepared for Newman's Indian Bradshaw, 1920. Some notations in EHW's handwriting.
    - Folder 13
      - "The distribution of the trees in Kuishu" by J. Miyoshi, with letter to EHW, dated November 5, 1915. (Added to Wilson papers, 1989.)
    - Folder 14
      - "Forest distribution in Chosen." Keijyo, 1915. (Added to Wilson papers, 1989.)
- W.XI: Legal Documents for Expeditions, 1899-1910
  - Box 18
    - Folder 1
      - Certificate of Registration. Issued by the British Consulate in Chungking, 1903. In English.
    - Folder 2
      - Certificate of Registration. Issued by the British Consulate in Ichang, 1904.
    - Folder 3
      - Agreement between EHW and a Chinese assistant "Boy-Cook," written in English and Chinese. The English version is written in Wilson's hand, 1904.
    - Folder 4
      - Copy of a letter from the Prince of Ching to Mr. Fletcher concerning a permit for EHW to export stuffed bird skins from China. In English. Dated November 5, 1907.
    - Folder 5
      - Four red calling cards EHW used in China, spelling his name phonetically. One 8x10 black and white print of Wilson's calling card.
    - Folder 6
      - USDA Official Papers for Agricultural Explorer for EHW. October 28, 1913.
      - Letter of Introduction from the American Embassy in Japan. February 5, 1914.
    - Folder 7
      - Chinese Travel Documents (Railway Tickets?)
    - Folder 8
      - Permission to export from Southern Rhodesia, January 18, 1922.
      - Receipts of purchased goods, 1909, 1922.
  - Box 18 Oversize
    - Folder 1
      - Travel permit issued in Canton, 1899.
    - Folder 2
      - Travel permit issued in 1899 for travels in Yunnan.
    - Folder 3
      - Travel permit issued in Hupeh province, 1900.
    - Folder 4
      - Travel permit issued in Ichang, 1900. (Framed, digital copy on wall across from the Library office.) Translation of this document is available in Folder 4.
    - Folder 5
      - Travel document issued for a Chinese assistant in Ichang, 1900.
    - Folder 6
      - Similar document for another Chinese assistant, 1900.
    - Folder 7
      - Travel document issued for a Chinese assistant, 1901.
    - Folder 8
      - Travel permit issued for EHW and Walter Reaves Zappey. The permit includes permission to carry hunting guns and cartridges. Ichang, 1908. (Framed, digital copy on wall across from the Library office.)
    - Folder 9
      - Travel permit issued in Peking, 1910. A translation is available in this folder. (Framed, digital copy on wall across from the Library office.)
    - Folder 10
      - Four identical "Notice to the Public" documents (in Chinese). Chungking, 1910.
- W.XII: Manuscripts: 1903-1904
  - Box 18
    - Folder 1
      - "Chungking," May 22-June 19, 1903. (82 pages in two parts)
    - Folder 2
      - "Kiating to Washan: en route to Tatien-lu," June 23-June 30, 1903. (16 pages)
    - Folder 3
      - "Fulin to the Tung Valley: en route to Tatien-lu," July 8-July 11, 1903. (10 pages)
    - Folder 4
      - "Wa-ssu kuo to Tatien-lu," July 14, 1903. (3 pages)
    - Folder 5
      - "A stretch of the Tung Valley," no date. (5 pages)
    - Folder 6
      - "The Min Valley: Kuan Hsien to Sungpan Ting," August 17-August 20, 1903. (17 pages).
      - "The Min Valley: Kuan Hsien to Sungpan Ting," August 22-August 27, 1903. (14 pages)
    - Folder 7
      - "Chentu to Sungpan via Sun...?" August 15-23, 1904. (13 pages)
    - Folder 8
      - "Lungan-Fu Song?" Sungpan, August 24-31, 1904. (19 pages)
    - Folder 9
      - Untitled manuscript containing general lecture on China, no date. (28 pages).
      - Typed copy of the same lecture, no date.
- W.XIII: Unpublished Manuscript and Related Correspondence, 1928-present.
  - Box 19
    - Folder 1
      - Manuscript to the unpublished "Wilson plants in cultivation." (2 photocopies of the original typed manuscript.) Table of contents/index compiled by Richard Howard. (Received March 1989.) One copy of Wilson manuscript given by Barbara Abbott to Arboretum while Peter Ashton was director.
  - Box 20
    Correspondence with horticulturists in England and one French gardener. Each folder contains all or part of the following: a) a letter from the horticulturist, b) a copy of letter from Wilson to the person who filled in the questionnaire, c) a questionnaire. Correspondents are listed alphabetically.
    - Folder 1a
      - Balfour, F.R.S.
    - Folder 2a, b, c
      - Bean, W.J.
    - Folder 3a, b, c
      - Beckett, Edwin.
    - Folder 4a, c
      - Besant, J.W.
    - Folder 5a, c
      - Chenault, Leon.
    - Folder 6a, c
      - Clarke, S.R.
    - Folder 7c
      - (No name) "Edinburgh."
    - Folder 8c
      - Eley, Charles.
    - Folder 9a
      - Hillier & Sons.
    - Folder 10a, b, c
      - Johnston, George.
    - Folder 11a, b, c
      - Loder, Gerald W.
    - Folder 12a
      - John Sterling (Pollok House).
    - Folder 13a
      - McDonall, Kenneth.
    - Folder 14a, b, c
      - McLaren, H.D. The letter from EHW to McLaren in this folder contains the following sentence: "Since we started last November [1928] we have covered about 225 plants with about 1000 more to go."
    - Folder 15a, c
      - Millais, J.G.
    - Folder 16a, b, c
      - Moore, H.A.
    - Folder 17a, b
      - Ramsden, Sir John.
    - Folder 18a, b, c
      - Williams, J.C.
    - Folder 19a, b, c
      - Williams, P.D.
    - Folder 20
      - A typed manuscript on the Rhododendrons of Western China.
    - Folder 21
      - Copy of typed manuscript in Folder 20.
    - Folder 22
      - Notes on Lily observations, in EHW's handwriting.
    - Folder 23
      - A list of plants, in EHW's handwriting. The list is selected from Wilson's collection numbers: 300-1848 ( Ardisia-Aconitum ).
    - Folder 24
      - List of plantings; possibly in EHW's handwriting, 1913-1916.
    - Folder 25a
      - Four letters from George H.M. Lawrence, Bailey Hortorium, to George Slate (Wilson's son-in-law). This folder also contains two copies of George Slate's letters to Lawrence.
    - Folder 26
      - Copy of a letter from Richard Howard to Norton Batkin, suggesting illustrations in the proposed "Wilson plants in cultivation." "E.H. Wilson and the 'Nodding Lilac'—Yearbook of the Lilac Society." By Richard A. Howard.
  - Box 20
    - Folder 27
      - Correspondence between Stephen A. Spongberg and Robert E. Cook relating to EHW's unpublished manuscript.
      - Copy of Spongberg's working manuscript based on EHW's unpublished manuscript.
- W.XIV: Ernest Henry Wilson Correspondence, 1899-1930., This correspondence series is divided into six subseries: A-F. Boxes: 15-19.
  - Subseries W.XIV:A: Letters written by Ernest Henry Wilson in the field to the Arnold Arboretum. Most of the letters are addressed to Charles Sprague Sargent; a few are addressed to Alfred Rehder. Arranged chronologically. 1906-1922.
    - Box 21, NOTE: Folders 8-10 contain letters written by Wilson during his sixth expedition to the Far East. 1917-1919. (67 letters total); NOTE: Folders 11-15 contain letters written by Wilson to the Arnold Arboretum during his expedition to the Southern Hemisphere. "The Gardens of the World." 1920-1922. (87 letters total)